Holocaust Collection 0008.003.004a
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
- Series II: Survivors
  - Survivors/ Klein, Gerda Weissmann, 1994; Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    Klein, Gerda Weissmann, Author, Journalist; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
- Series III: Commemorations
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Mandala Project, West Hartford, 1976; Manuscripts, pamphlets (Box 3)
    This folder contains programs and a scrapbook pertaining to the "Holocaust or Hope (A Rededication)" program sponsored by the West Hartford Human Rights Commision and the Hartford Jewish Federation.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Jewish Federation of Greater Hartford; Mandala Project
  - Commemorations/ Connecticut /March of the Living/Kafer, Jared, 2006; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    Avon Life newspaper magazine article (08/2006) featuring the story of Jared Kafer's visit to Poland and his high school senior mastery project on the "March of the Living".
    Kafer, Jared, Physician; Holocaust -- Second Generation
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Memos, flyers, programs, 1960s, 1962-1968; Original program flyers (Box 3)
    Folder contains series of program flyers of associated with Holocaust anniversary remembrance ceremonies sponsored by the Jewish Community Center (JCC).
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Jewish Community Center
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Memos, flyers, programs, 1970s, 1970-1979; Program flyers and announcements (Box 3)
    Folder contains a series of program flyers associated with Holocaust remembrance ceremonies sponsored by the Jewish Community Center. Additionally, a poster advertising the performance of Brundibar at the JCC.
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Memos, flyers, programs, 1980s, 1980-1989; Program flyers, newsletters, announcements; Cargas, Harry James (Box 3)
    Folder contains materials pertaining to Holocaust commemorations during the 1980s. Included are program flyers to the Holocaust Commemorations of the State of Connecticut and a manuscript entitled "A Christian Response to the Holocaust" written by Dr. Harry James Cargas.
    Yale University.; Commemorations/ Memorials; Emanuel Synagogue; Holocaust; Jewish Community Center; Oral History
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Memos, flyers, programs, 1990s, 1990-1999; Bernstein, Norman J., Attorney (Box 3)
    Folder contains a series of flyers and announcements related to Holocaust commemorations in West Hartford and at the CT state level. Additionally there are manuscript materials including poems and other related materials attributed to Norman J. Bernstein, West Hartford attorney.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Emanuel Synagogue; Holocaust; Jewish Community Center
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Memos, flyers, programs, 2000s, 2000-2006; Program flyers (Box 3)
    Folder contains a series of flyers and announcements related to Holocaust commemorations in West Hartford and at the CT state level.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Emanuel Synagogue; Holocaust
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1940s, 1943-1949; Newspaper clippings; Silverman, Morris, Rabbi (Box 3)
    Hartford Courant articles dating back to the 1940's discussing Holocaust remembrance.
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1950s, 1951; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    Folder contains 1951 newspaper article featuring story of Jewish honor being attributed to Polish-born Hartford resident, Joseph Psutka.
    AvRutick, Abraham, Rabbi, Russia; Feldman, Abraham J., Rabbi, b.1893, Ukraine, Russia; Silverman, Morris, Rabbi; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1970s, 1970-1979; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    This folder contains several newspaper articles related to Holocaust commemorations throughout the 1970's. Includes several group photos of important figureheads in the Jewish community.
    Berenbaum, Michael; Bodenheimer, Hans, Rabbi, Germany; Grasso, Ella; Kopman, Helen, Warsaw, Poland; Koret, Arthur, Cantor, Hartford, CT; Poupko, Bernard, Rabbi, Doctor; Silver, Harold, Rabbi; Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor; Commemorations/ Memorials; Education; Hadassah; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Temple Beth Israel
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1980s, 1980-1989; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    This folder contains a sizable collection of Holocaust commemoration related newspaper articles, featuring many notable activists and Jewish community leaders.
    AvRutick, Abraham, Rabbi, Russia; Berenbaum, Michael; Bodenheimer, Hans, Rabbi, Germany; Gaster, Berthold, Journalist/The Ledger, b.1926, Vienna; Jacobs, Fred; Kennelly, Barbara; Konover, Simon; Koret, Arthur, Cantor, Hartford, CT; Lazowski, Phillip; Leopold, Max; Stein, Merrill; Tabatsky, Israel, Cantor; Commemorations/ Memorials; Congregation Tikvoh Chadoshoh; Education; Emanuel Synagogue; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Jewish Community Center; Krystallnacht
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1990s, 1990-1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    Gaster, Berthold, Journalist/The Ledger, b.1926, Vienna; Green, David, Cantor; Jacobs, Fred; Lazowski, Phillip; Lindenthal, Haskel, Rabbi; Shainfarber, George; Commemorations/ Memorials; Emanuel Synagogue; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors; Krystallnacht; Yom Hashoah
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 2000s, 2000-2010; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    This folder contains a series of newspaper articles related to Holocaust commemorations on the local and state levels.
    Jacobs, Fred; Klein, Gerda Weissmann, Author, Journalist; Lazowski, Phillip; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Holocaust survivors
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Weinberg, Elbert sculpture on ground of JCCGH, 1981; Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    This folder contains newspaper articles related to the dedication of the JCC Holocaust memorial sculpture designed by Elbert Weinberg.
    Chase, David T.; Jacobs, Regina; Kennelly, Barbara; Weinberg, Elbert, Sculptor; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/West Hartford/Proclamation by Mayor Kevin Sullivan, April 1985, Original document mounted on foamboard; Gaster, Adele Diane; Sullivan, Kevin B., Mayor (Box 3)
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; West Hartford, CT; Yom Hashoah
  - Commemorations/Connecticut/Yom Shoah Commemoration, 2000; Photocopied documents, newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    Folder contains a copy of the Yom HaShoah Commemoration: Life Before the War teaching materials. Included are maps, suggested reading lists, personal survivor recollections, and historical abstracts.
    Beth El Temple; Education; Greater Hartford Jewish Community Center; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Jewish Federation of Greater Hartford; Maps; Yom Hashoah
  - Commemorations/General/European, 1994-1995; Newspaper clippings; Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor (Box 3)
    Folder contains newspaper articles reporting 50 year commemorations of the liberation of Auschwitz.
    Auschwitz; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Holocaust survivors; Nazi concentration camps
  - Commemorations/General/March of the Living, 1988, Newspaper clippings; Gaster, Adele Diane (Box 3)
    Folder contains Jewish Ledger articles, some written by Adele Gaster, reporting on teen participation in the "March of the Living".
    Auschwitz; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Nazi concentration camps
  - Commemorations/General/March of the Living, 2008, Newspaper clippings (Box 3)
    Folder contains newspaper articles featuring Hartford teenager participation in 2008 March of the Living from Auschwitz to Birkenau on Yom HaShoah.
    Auschwitz; Holocaust -- Second Generation; Nazi concentration camps
  - Commemorations/National, 1985-1995; Newspaper clippings; Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor (Box 3)
    Folder contains a variety of Holocaust related articles. Included is a full length article written by Elie Wiesel discussing his recollections on the 40th year commemoration of the liberation of Auschwitz. Also in this folder is a full copy of a newspaper entitled "Together" sponsored and published by the American Gathering of Jewish Holocaust Survivors. Dated December 1994, this paper contains a wealth of information related to Holocaust commemoration during this time period.
- Series IV: Education
  - Education/Connecticut/Colleges and Libraries, 1978-1995; Newspaper clippings and course syllabus (Box 4)
    Folder includes newspaper aticles related to events and indivduals related to local colleges and the Holocaust. Included is a 1978 non-credit Trinity College course syllabus "The Nazi Holocaust and Its Challenges to Contemporary Education".
    Dwork, Deborah, College Professor, Doctor; Trinity University.; University of Connecticut. UCONN.; University of Hartford.; Yale University.; Education; Holocaust
  - Education/Connecticut/Miscellaneous, 1980-1990; Pamphlets and newspaper clippings (Box 4)
    Folder contains a series of newspaper articles related to Holocaust education events and a CT B'Nai B'rith newsletter magazine entitled " Committee on Holocaust Awareness". Also included is a guide to publications and audio/visual materials on the Holocaust published by the Anti-Defamation League of B'Nai B'rith.
    Anti-Defamation League; B'nai B'rith; Holocaust
  - Education/Connecticut/Museums and Libraries, 1985; Newspaper articles (Box 4)
    Folder contains newspaper articles from 1985 discussing events and artifacts related to the Holocaust.
    Holocaust; Nazi concentration camps; Visual Arts
  - Education/Connecticut/Museums and libraries/JHSGH Holocaust room, 1990s; Brochures and notes (Box 4)
    Folder contains notes and memorandums related to the creation of the JHSGH Holocaust exhibit room.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
  - Education/Connecticut/Newspaper clippings, 1990s-2000s; Newspaper clippings; Soumerai, Eve (Box 4)
    This folder contains a series of newspaper articles featuring stories concerning the Holocaust and education in CT
    Education; Holocaust
  - Education/Connecticut/Teaching for a Better World," resource book, 1999; bound booklet; University of Hartford. (Box 4)
    This folder contains a University of Hartford college course and research guide on the subject of the Holocaust entitled, "Teaching for a Better World: Why and How to Teach the Holocaust", created by Lynn K. McMullin and Myra Rabinovitz.
  - Education/Connecticut/Voices of Hope, 2010; Brochure; Voices of Hope. (Hartford, CT) (Box 4)
  - Education/International/Israel Information Center/package of educational materials, 1995-1996, 2000; Pamphlets (Box 4)
    This collection of pamphlets and magazines provides a general overview of Jewish life during the Holocaust. Includes maps and other historical documentation.
    Education; Holocaust; Israel
  - Education/International/Museums and Libraries/Miscellaneous, 1999; Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
    Jewish Ledger article (07/16/1999) featuring Peter Eisenmann, New York architect participating in the design of the Berlin Holocaust Memorial.
    Eisenmann, Peter, Architect; Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust
  - Education/National/Florida/Middle School Curriculum, 1984; Bound paperback book 9" x 11" (Box 4)
    This folder contains an interdisciplinary cirriculum unit plan for middle school students entitled, The Holocaust: Lessons for the Future. This educational unit plan was written and developed by Karen L. Riley, (cover design by Susan L. Riley). Lessons included are interdisciplinary, covering subjects of Social Studies, English, Math, and Science as such related to Holocaust studies.
  - Education/National/Florida/The Holocaust Memorial Resource and Education Center of Central Florida, 1990; Bound paperback 9" x 11" book (Box 4)
    This folder contains an extensive bibliography of materials related to the Holocaust. Table of Contents: I. After the Holocaust: Reflections and Literary Analysis II. America and the Jews III. Anti-Semitism and Prejudice IV. Art of the Holocaust 1. Art 2. Drama 3. Music 4. Photography 5. Poetry V. Camps VI. Children in the Holocaust VII. Children's Literature VIII. Christianity and the Holocaust IX. Chronicles, Diaries, Memoirs X. Collaboration and Indifference XI. Collections - Miscellaneous XII. Controlled Society - Studies in Tyranny XIII. Curriculum Materials and Reference XIV. Genocide - Case Studies XV. Ghettos XVI. History XVII. Holocaust: History; Studies XVIII. In Hiding XIX. Israel XX. Jews, History XXI. Literature of the Holocaust XXII. Liturgies
  - Education/National/Museums and libraries/Miscellaneous Material, undated; Miscellaneous publications, articles, and institutional brochures; Center for Holocaust Studies. (Brooklyn, NY); Holocaust Memorial Center. (Bloomfield, MI); Jewsih Genealogical Society of Canada.; Simon Wiesenthal Center. (Los Angeles, California); United States Holocaust Memorial Council. (Washington, D.C.) (Box 4)
    This folder contains brochures, newspaper articles, and other related educational booklets pertaining to the Holocaust experience. Included is booklet published by Yad Vashem and a publication of art, music and poetry entitled "This Shall Tell All the Ages".
    American Jewish Congress; Commemorations/ Memorials; Education; Holocaust; Music; Poetry; U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum; Yad Vashem - Jerusalem
  - Education/National/Museums and libraries/Texas, 1990-1991; Newsletters, catalogs, photos; Dallas Memorial Center for Holocaust Studies. (Dallas, Texas) (Box 4)
    This folder contains catalogs and newsletters created by the Dallas Memorial Center for Holocaust Studies. Included are photos depicting the memorial exhibit room belonging to the center in Dallas, TX.
  - Education/National/Museums and Libraries/Washington DC/National Holocaust Museum, 1989-1993; Newspaper clippings, booklets, newsletters (Box 4)
    This series folder contains newspaper and magazine articles related to the U.S. Holocaust Museum in Washington, D.C. Included are mock passports of Jews relating their Holocaust experiences.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Education; Holocaust; U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum
  - Education/National/National/President's Commission on the Holocaust, 1979, Booklets and magazine article; Wiesel, Elie, Author, Doctor (Box 4)
    This folder contains a published report to the President from the Commission on the Holocaust and magazine articles related to this event. The report was submitted by Chairman Elie Wiesel, dated September 27, 1979, and was co-signed by several prominent representatives of the Jewish community.
    Holocaust; Politics
  - Education/National/Publications/miscellaneous advertisements, 1972-1988; Newsletters, advertisements, publications (Box 4)
    This folder contains newsletters, event advertisements, and other materials related to publications pertaining to the Holocaust.
- Series V: Poland
  - Poland/Children/Booklet: The World Remembers Those Children, 1971; Booklet with photographs
    Folder contains publication by the Council for the Protection of Monuments to Struggle and Martyrdom documenting the plight of Polish children during the Holocaust.
    Commemorations/ Memorials; Holocaust; Poland
  - "Jwei Mark", money used in Ghetto, 1940; Artifact object and photocopy (Box 5)
    Folder contains original "Jwei mark" issued in Litzmannstadt, May 15th, 1940.
    Holocaust; Living in a Ghetto
  - Poland/Miscellaneous, 1987-1995; Newspaper clippings and booklet; Polish American Congress Charitable Foundation. (Chicago, Illinois) (Box 5)
    This folder contains miscellaneous news articles related to Polish post-Holocaust experience.
    Holocaust; Poland
  - Poland/Warsaw Ghetto Uprising/Miscellaneous published materials and newspaper clippings, 1952-1993; Newspaper clippings, newsletters, booklets (Box 5)
    This folder contains a variety of materials related to and commemorating the Warsaw Ghetto uprising, April 19, 1943. Included are materials published by the World Jewish Congress (1953) and the Congress Bi-Weekly (1963).
    Anniversaries; Holocaust; Warsaw Ghetto uprising
  - Poland/Warsaw Ghetto/Yosell Rackover's "Yossel Rackover's Appeal to God", 1957; Booklet publication (Box 5)
    An April 1957 excerpt from the Jewish Digest and from the book, "The Tiger Beneath the Skin" by Zvi Kolitz. This excerpt, fully entitled "The Last Thoughts of a Jew Who Died in the Warsaw Ghetto, Yossel Rackover's Appeal to God" was reprinted by permission, Houston, Texas.
    Holocaust testimony
  - Witnesses/Connecticut/Chapman, William, undated; Newspaper clipping (Box 5)
    Folder contains undated newspaper article featuring a story on Capt. William A. Chapman of Bloomfield, CT and his experience returning to German concentration camps after the war.
    Chapman, William; Holocaust; Jewish War Veterans
  - Witnesses/Connecticut/Hayes, John F., undated; Handwritten correspondence (Box 5)
    Folder contains a handwritten testimony by Hayes concerning atrocities he witnessed as a soldier in WWII.
    Hayes, John F.; Holocaust testimony
  - Witnesses/Connecticut/Matlock, Carl, 1994-1995; photocopies (Box 5)
    Folder contains copies of original oversized articles featuring stories on concentration camp liberation.
    Mattock, Carl; Holocaust -- Liberation
- Series VI: Exhibits
  - Anne Frank and the World exhibit, undated (Box 6)
- Series VII: Exhibits
  - Anne Frank and the World exhibit and the Holocaust Memorial Room, undated (Box 7)
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook containing newspaper clippings about various Holocaust observances, 1980s., undated
- Series IX: Oversize
  - Miscellaneous oversize documents related to the Holocaust, undated
- Series X: Double Oversize
  - Educational posters from Yad Vashem exhibit related to the Holocaust and Nuremberg trials., undated
- Photo Series I: Holocaust Photographs, 7 folders
  - Commemorations & Memorials, 1980s; 3 photos (Box 1)
    Holocaust commemoration at Connecticut State House, c. 1985
    Synagogue commemoration of Holocaust, c.1983
    Postcard - memorial monnument at Bergen-Belsen, a Nazi concentration camp, 1950s
    Holocaust commemoration, 1977
    Ct State House Holocaust Commemorative Observance, 1979 (two images -- one featuring CT Governer, Ella Grasso)
    Grasso, Ella; Commemorations/ Memorials; Connecticut, USA; Holocaust
  - General/contemporary scenes, 1940s, 1946-1949; 3 photos (Box 1)
    First Anniversary of State of Israel recognized in Munich, Germany, 1949 (2 photos)
    Althea Silverman with survivors in front of ovens at Auschwitz, 1946
    Silverman, Althea, Teacher, Utica, NY; Silverman, Morris, Rabbi; Holocaust; Israel; Nazi concentration camps
  - General/File photographs of Anne Frank, 1940s; 3 Photos w/ multiple portrait copies (Box 1)
    Anne Frank at school desk
    Anne Frank portrait closeup -- 2 views
  - General/Jewish Museum/file photographs of Nazi era, 1939/1981; 5 photos 8" x 10" (some w/ copies) (Box 1)
    Photo image of Judisches Gemeindeblatt newsleaf concerning end of Danzig synagogue
    1981 American anti-semites
    Nazis marching in Danzig, Germany (w/ copy)
    Pidyon Ha-ben Plate, brass-engraved
    Storefront in Danzig depicting German anti-semitism
    Precious Legacy Smithsonian exhibit_sorting through possessions 1943
    photocopy of book cover "From the Family Album, 1990" (located in oversize II)
    Anti-Semitism; Nazis/ Nazi Germany; pre-Nazi Germany
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Weiss, Mr. and Mrs. Nandor, photocopies, 1943; photocopies (Box 1)
    Weiss, Nandor; Holocaust survivors; Labor Camps; Weddings
  - Survivors/Connecticut/Weiner, Ruth Frosh (kindertransport, Gibber student), 1940s-1950; 1 photo 3" x 5" (Box 1)
    General note
    Photo of Ms. Weiner with label on back noting "Gibber Street" and "Kindertransport".
    Weiner, Ruth Frosh; Holocaust survivors
  - Mandala Project/West Hartford, 1976, undated; several photographs (Box 1)
- Photo Series II: Europe and Holocaust Photographs
  - Europe and Holocaust/Antepolye, Grodno, 1929 by David Sherry, originals and negatives, multiple original photos w/ negatives; Caution! The negatives in this set are "nitrate negatives", which are highly flammable. If they show signs of deterioration (stickiness or oozing) contact a professional archival conservator immediately. (New England Document Conservation Center, Andover, MA (978)-470-1010.; Sherry, David (Box 2)
    Custodial History note
    Collection created by David Sheery was donated by Mrs. Myer Rogoroff, January 1978.
    This collection consists of multiple photographs depicting rural Jewish peasant life in Poland and Russia, c. 1929. Photos are original, w/ negatives.
    SOME GENERAL COMMENTS ON THE THREE SHTETLACH IN GRODNO GEBERNYEH
    By Rebecca Litfshitz
    These pictures are of three towns:Kobrin, Horodetz, and Antipolia. These shtetlach were situated in Polesiyeh Region in the state of Grodno.
    KOBRIN Kobrin was the largest of the three. It had a bigger Jewish population, a high school, and institutions of higher Jewish learning. Kobrin also had a movie house. The town had small factories. The Jews mostly made a living as merchants, shoemakers, tailors, carpenters, and teachers of the Torah. HORODETZ
    Horodetz was located on the Dnepper-Burgsky Canal. It also had a train station not far from the center of town. Both of these helped bring commerce to the area. Like all the small towns, it had centers of Jewish study. Horodetz produced authors, artists, and musicians such as Jan Peerce who was born there.
    ANTIPOLIA Antipolia was bigger than Horodetz and had more Jewish inhabitants. In 1914 a commercial high school was opened as well as a four-year preparatory school before high s school for girls. There was a Talmud Torah and private teachers and rabbis who ran schools to teach the children Hebrew and Jewish history. The schools opened at 8 a.m. and closed at 8 p.m., and learning went on for a l2-hour period. Two Hebrew news- storekeepers, workers, blacksmiths, and other types of workers. Some were merchants that boughts and sold grain; others dealt with lumber. Several Jews rented farms and worked the land since they themselves couldn't own the land; many were dairy farners. These Jews had a better standard of living. Youths who sought higher education came to this shtetl to be instructed.They ate in the middle-class homes and slept on the hard benches in the synagogues. In these three towns were ardent Zionists who worked for their ideals and donated all they could for the cause. On Saturdays the middle-class Jews would gather in a house. They would discuss religion and politics and play chess. The tragedy of today is that these shtetlach are without any Jews. Although they produced well-educated, talented, and devoted Jews for many years before World Var II, the Holocaust erased all signs of Jewish life there.
    Holocaust; Jewish life in Europe; pre-Nazi Europe; pre-Nazi Germany; Shtetl life
  - Europe and Holocaust/Antepolye, Grodno, 1929 by David Sherry, 4 folders, blow-up copies of originals; Sherry, David (Box 2)
    Holocaust; Jewish life in Europe; pre-Nazi Europe; Shtetl life
  - Europe and Holocaust/Funeral in Russia, 1905, 1 photograph copy and original negative (Box 2)
    This photo comes from an unidentified town in Russia. This couple, who were the only people in their village who had a coal stove, were asphixiated. [Note bodies wrapped in shrouds]
    Provenance
    Donated by Morris Perkel, 7/18/1973
    Perkel, Morris, b.3/12/1899, Russia; Funeral services
  - Europe and Holocaust/Gravestone of Esther Einstein, Poland, c. 1928, undated; original negative with copy (Box 2)